In this video clip I would be setting up the sole.
The sole is the very base of our plane.
Now we need this to be as flat as possible so we can get nice cuts.
First, thing we need to do is retract the blade using the depth adjustment lever.
Next we are going to take a permanent marker and color the bottom.
I like to use red cause it shows up a little bit better.
Next we are going to take 180 grit piece of sand paper and we are going to rub the plane on the sand paper for about 30 seconds.
Now when you do this you want to make sure that your sand paper is on a true surface.
I'm using a table saw in this case.
Now when you flip it over after about 30 seconds the areas that are still pretty dark red are going to be low areas that need to be fixed.
To fix it you are going to continue working the plane on the sand paper until all the red areas are completely gone.
Once all the red is gone you are going to move on to a 220 grit sand paper and even a finer grit sand paper and you are going to continue this until you get a nice smooth finish on the sole of your plane.